this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software developers are you ready it's
time to upgrade your data platform to
inner systems iris choose your language
choose your tools choose your
environment collaborate build faster and
deploy more efficiently when you can
make faster decisions there's no telling
what you'll create ready set code start
coding for free visit inner systems comm
slash try to try iris
hey this is Jeremy Jung for software
engineering radio today I'm speaking
with Sarah lien
Sarah is a localization programmer for
exeed games she's also been working in
the games industry for over ten years
I'll be speaking with Sarah about her
experience translating games from
Japanese to English adding improvements
to them and porting them to different
platforms Sarah welcome to software
engineering radio thank you for having
me the first thing I want to start with
is you have experience with building
other types of software I was kind of
taking a look at your resume what makes
games different than working on a
typical software application well in
general with games there's a lot of
things that you have to worry about that
you otherwise wouldn't like the frame
rate of the application becomes very
important for example you need to make
sure that the timer's of the application
are coded just so that the game will
always run at a steady pace and there
are various applications of timers like
Delta time that are usually used to
ensure this goes perfectly smooth and so
when you talk about timers I've heard of
this concept of like a game loop is that
kind of what you're referring to or
could you elaborate a little bit well
essentially a game of course is made of
graphics audio and input but all of
these have to be checked every frame and
so you have your timer going so that it
is basically looping through the game
sixty times a second or whatever other
frame rate your game is running at a lot
run at thirty there will be various
steps in this process like game logic
and drawing the various models and of
course you have to keep the sound system
updating so it's like as opposed to say
a web application where a lot of things
are in response to something right
somebody going to a web page clicking a
button with a game it sounds like there
is this sort of consistent loop I guess
that's tied to the frame rate is that
correct right
and instead of reacting to things you
are occasionally checking the state of
course you know so many times per frame
and you will still have to respond to
the user input but it's all going to be
one part of this large set of functions
if I understand correctly so you're
basically in this this loop and let's
say somebody was pressing a button under
controller or moving their Mouse like
that would affect the state and when
you're in that loop it's going to look
at that state to determine what to do
next in the loop is that yes exactly for
example in your input system you are
usually going to be saving every frame
the state of the input system at the
moment like is this button being pushed
is this button being pushed was this
button pushed last frame and by
comparing it against the previous frame
you know what the user is doing right
now and then many parts of the game
logic will have various branches that
check exactly what the user is inputting
and what the current context is it's
certainly more complex than the idea of
I push a button and it calls this
function that sounds like like an
entirely different model of thinking I
guess I guess the structure of the
application has to be almost completely
different absolutely
in terms of skill sets on working on a
game versus working on a regular
application what parts are really
different and which parts are kind of
the same well essentially regardless of
what you're working on you're going to
be working with a lot of external api's
but these are probably going to be
entirely different for a game versus
other software for example you need to
be familiar with api's like directx and
opengl and all of these typically have
different ways of handling graphics
handling audio handling input there's
also SDL of course that you could use
and depending Iowa on the programming
language as well there may be different
ways of handling certain things that
would be different from handling a
normal application but most importantly
you need to be familiar
with graphics and audio api's above all
I think I think those are typically less
important when you're working on normal
software because you're more concerned
about how to build your window and how
to get all the elements displaying in
the proper positions I guess with a
typical application the actual act of
rendering to the screen is sort of
abstracted away from you so you don't
actually have to worry about how to draw
to the screen it's sort of more like I
just want a button or I just want a
window and something else is handling
that for you yes that's pretty much it
and when it comes to video game graphics
you have to consider a lot of different
things like differences between graphics
cards can this graphics card handle
square textures or does it need a
different shape as well of course as
being concerned with the quality of how
its drawing like is this texture
supposed to be filtered will this
graphics card filter it correctly the
API simplify that but you're working at
a lower level and when you're giving
examples of API as you were talking
about directx and opengl and SDL how low
a level are we talking like if I wanted
to draw something to the screen kind of
at the most base level
what kind of work am i looking at well
for SDL in particular this is somewhat
of a simplified process because it
handles all of the initialization of
devices and such for you
but with directx and opengl you have to
actually get the list of devices you
have to initialize each process that you
need like you need direct3d you need
direct input you need direct sound and
then you know you have to make sure that
you have all the device information that
you need including stuff like the
current resolution or the capabilities
of the device device capabilities is a
big thing when it comes to that and then
to actually draw the image you are going
to need to create a texture buffer
you're going to need a back buffer for
the screen and then you will have to
load the texture and you will have to
draw the
sure to the buffer and then present that
to the screen when you refer to the
buffer I just kind of a high-level can
you kind of explain what that's doing
well essentially you have the screen
that you're drawing to and you usually
don't want every single draw command to
go directly to the screen it's better to
have a buffer that you can operate with
so that you can display things in the
correct order at all times you can have
them on the correct sea level and of
course any sort of processing you need
to do you can do before it's drawn to
the screen and so everything goes onto
the buffer after it's you know ready
more or less and so when something is in
the buffer is that kind of like and
that's what you plan to actually have
the video card render or is that like
after it's already been rendered where's
that in the stage
well rendering is basically the last
step of presentation but it depends if
you are drawing something 3d naturally
you are going to have to do some
processing on that via the graphics card
and the API is allowed for things like
that but typically rendering to the
screen itself is always going to be the
very last step of the frame mmm okay and
then elsewhere in your application
you're deciding even though you're
putting things into the buffer you're
deciding that maybe there are certain
frames that you don't actually need to
render yeah and of course that depends
highly on the game but often there may
be no difference so you don't really
need a new frame or there might be a
case where the game is overall running a
little too slow so skipping some of
these frames will get you more CPU
cycles free to work with okay you know
we were talking about the loop earlier
we're sort of all the logic is happening
at a set rate but in terms of the way
people see the game in terms of how
smooth it is you may have the game logic
running at the same rate but only choose
to render certain frames in the buffer
so it it still runs the same as just
that it's a little bit jerky or choppier
yeah and essentially you need your game
logic working at the highest that your
gameplay can really go mm-hmm but when
it comes to the graphics it's a little
more arbitrary for sure there are
situations where you might intentionally
want your game logic running at a
hundred and twenty frames per second
instead and then the player input and
such will still come at that speed
regardless of the actual refresh rate of
the display mmm interesting I want to
talk a little bit about how games can
have a lot of binary assets typical
software development you would use git
as a version control system would you
use the same for games or is there a
different system that's more suitable
well naturally this depends on the
company quite a few do use git and
simply store the binary assets even
though there is no real comparison
system for them and as far as that goes
there are also various internal systems
that companies may use that are
specially made for handling their
specific assets and essentially version
control is not actually that different
in the gaming industry it just
occasionally uses different applications
okay and so when somebody uses yeah even
with the binary asses it's not an issue
that you just can't see the the dips
properly
oh no it's typically not a big deal
because I'm it's not difficult to look
at two different pictures and visually
compare them and you know generally
you're going to be changing the binary
as it's less as development goes on
rather than more where's the code that's
always gonna be changing mm-hmm so the
title you use is localization programmer
so what would you say is the main role
of a localization programmer well
essentially when a game is being
localized from one language to another
obviously the goal is that you get all
of the text inserted and you make sure
that it all looks correct at base levels
this is generally the accepted
position of a localization programmer
you are getting all of the text into the
game you are making all of the code work
with the correct fonts and other asset
changes that you may need that are
different from the original language
however there are a lot of things in
this process that you wouldn't normally
need as a skill for example if you are
working with Japanese gains all of the
comments and everything are going to be
in Japanese of course that kind of
brings me to when you're translating
games do you usually have access to the
original source code I usually do but
there are plenty of cases where we are
working on a game and the original
developer is actually the one to handle
the localized version it depends a lot
on how much other companies feel they
are able to release to other parties
whether it's because of rights issues or
they're just kind of nervous about the
code quality which I mean I would be and
when you get access to the code do you
usually have access to the original
developers are you kind of on your own I
would say that that completely varies
you never know exactly but it's usually
gonna be the same with each partner like
they will usually be more than happy to
help you if they have the developers on
hand to help you but with game companies
of course they are constantly developing
new titles themselves so when someone
like me is working on a game we may not
have as much access to the developers or
they would be working on the game and so
you were talking earlier about being
able to extract text or bring text into
the game what are some examples of ways
that the the text would already be
stored and how would you bring that out
this also varies a lot and it's very
interesting many games use script files
essentially lists of commands for their
events etc and in these cases as long as
you know the format of the script file
you're usually going to be fine but some
games like to hard-code their text and
yet others have been in binary formats
that have been compiled in some way
assembled rather
mm-hmm and when that happens you often
have to take a look at the code and
figure out exactly what this format is
which may or may not be documented and
basically you do the process in Reverse
on assemble it the first example you
gave was script files so would that just
be like a plain text file and you could
go in and replace that text with you
know instead of Japanese put in English
essentially yes like when there's a
script file format you're going to see
various commands like there will be
message and then it will have the text
for a message box that kind of thing and
when that is the case it's usually
pretty easy to change since it is just
text but you might run into some
encoding issues by encoding issues would
that be where let's say you replace the
Japanese with English and then the game
itself tries to load the text from the
script file and it can't do to a
different text encoding not so much that
as you might get garbled text what in
the fan community that I used to work in
we would call cave speak could you kind
of explain what you mean by that imagine
that you are playing a game in Japanese
but your system doesn't have Japanese
fonts loaded the font not being there
for Japanese you might instead see
gibberish like ekv gah you know that
kind of thing okay and that is cave
speak and if the encoding is very
specific for the game or the font simply
doesn't have other symbols you might get
complete gibberish in what font was
already there in Japanese that's called
mochi baka the way that encodings work
of course is that the text is
interpreted from its binary or
hexadecimal format into characters we
can understand and since there's a lot
of different encodings out there
sometimes you don't know exactly what
you're going to get so for example if a
game was made for an older system it may
have a completely custom encoding where
a value
like two means a and in this situation
just replacing the text you have no idea
what the games gonna output you're gonna
have to change it all yourself I see so
it's like in the original I guess text
in the script files or perhaps you're
talking about the binary files they're
not necessarily using a standard
encoding like say ASCII or Unicode they
may have made up their own encoding
format yes and this certainly varies
when it comes to Japanese you'll usually
be able to find that it's in the
standard Japanese encoding shift-jis
and shift-jis largely supports English
letters but because Japanese text tends
to include characters that are all the
same width it doesn't often account for
the fact that in English you have very
thin letters like the letter I and so
when you simply insert the text into
those games you might get a situation
where all of the letters are spaced
really far from each other because the
the Japanese language each character has
the same width and height but in English
at vary so that's why everything gets
spaced out right you were talking about
how there's the example of script files
or the example of code being hard-coded
or maybe even binary files sort of what
is the like end result you'd like to you
know to get this text out for a
translator to work on what are you
trying to give to them for them to work
on typically the text you want to get
into an excel sheet because that's the
industry standard for translation and
keeping texts like that sometimes the
developer will provide this themselves
and that will of course make the process
of translation a little easier because
somebody like me can work while the game
is being translated but usually on it's
more case of what is the translator
comfortable working with like are they
comfortable working with script files do
they need
sell sheet most of them do and that's
fine but obviously this results in more
steps you need to create a tool chain to
both extract the text and get it into a
sheet and then you have to make the call
of whether you can get that text
directly back into the game or if you
would need to include more information
like the exact lines that's from the the
simplest I guess would be the script
file where you might build a tool to
convert the script files to rows in an
Excel spreadsheet a translator works on
that to translate it to English they
give the spreadsheet back to you and you
run some kind of application to convert
their spreadsheet back into the script
files yes exactly
although granted if the game is very
small you might just do it all by hand
hmm okay in terms of these script files
like are the lines of dialogue or the
text are they kind of in their original
context like if you know somebody in a
game was having a conversation with all
of the sentences kind of be grouped
together or is it sometimes just kind of
spread all over the place this varies a
lot sometimes you won't even know which
character is speaking unless you
actually play through the game while
you're working on the script well and
obviously this poses some interesting
challenges mm-hmm because in general
Japanese it's not as context heavy and
context apparent as English's you can't
always tell who's talking just by the
tone of their voice so to speak you know
going back to when you have something
where the text is hard-coded you know is
that a case where you basically have to
do it by hand or have you found a
process to deal with that there are a
variety of ways that this can be
approached too which is part of the
beauty of games it's an art form but
what I personally like to do is simply
make something that extracts all of the
apparent strings like surrounded by
quotes from all of the code and
gives that information along with the
line number and so just like with any
other script you can usually automate
this mmm I see so you you basically
create your own version of a script I
guess even though they didn't exist
originally yeah and then you have this
list of all the strings in the game and
you can easily put those into a sheet
when you work on localization how much
of the code base or the game engine do
you feel like you need to understand it
depends on the scope of the task but
typically I would say that I don't need
personally to understand much of the
game to start working on it but by the
time that the project is finished I
should understand almost everything
except for the raw graphics API is being
used even then I might need to depending
on how the game is functioning and
whether we need to do something
differently like making an older game
use widescreen and what's kind of your
strategy when you know you first start
work on a project you get the source
files and you need to find out where the
text is stored and and how it's stored
kind of what's your strategy for for
figuring that out first I will look
through all the files I received and
make sure that the text isn't somewhere
extremely obvious and if it's an obvious
I will then start looking at the source
code and getting it to compile and I
will look through that to see exactly
what files it's loading and from there I
can usually figure out where the text is
stored in terms of when you get a
project do you you just look at the code
or do you figure out like how to to run
it and all that first well usually I
prefer to start by looking at the code
itself and getting that to compile but
typically a developer will provide a
working copy of the game that you can
use to see exactly how everything
functions I do like to know what kind of
game I'm working on and the basics of
the gameplay the basics of the setting
because that
will help me motivate myself to work on
it it will help me get into the right
mindset for it you were talking about
how you know there were kind of easier
ways of localizing in terms of script
files and like maybe the hardest being
hard-coded or binary what are some ways
that if a developer's is making a game
that they can facilitate like the
easiest localization the easiest
localization would definitely be first
you want to make script files for
everything whether it's just the list of
strings that the game is using or a
proper script file for all the events
and then you want to make sure that the
game is capable of loading different
sets of these based on what language is
currently in use and if the game is
already capable of loading different
folders or different files for different
versions of the scripts then it
shouldn't be too hard to localize but
you also need to make sure that there
are easy ways to work with the graphics
and of course absolutely all of the
assets can be loaded differently based
on the language another problem of
course is when it comes down to stuff
like fonts because to make a very pretty
looking fonts you probably want to make
the font graphical rather than using a
true type or OpenType font and of course
the challenge with that is including
every character you could need for every
language as well as issues like the font
could be you know badly spaced in
certain languages and to make a game as
easy to localize as possible
you probably want to use unicode and
unicode fonts and just include
everything you possibly can mmm and
because unicode has most you know
languages used in the world and you
won't have the text encoding problem
exactly you would completely skip that
step you wouldn't need to worry about
the fonts you would just be able to put
whatever language you need and you won't
get tripped up by stuff like in Japanese
games shift-jis is the ink
used right and if you try to insert
accents like an you know like an e with
the little dash over it it will instead
draw a Japanese symbol if you don't
change the encoding mmm I see you were
talking about graphical fonts so would
that be like a raster image like a giant
PNG or a jpg that has all the different
characters on it is that kind of how
that would work yes exactly
usually this also has some sort of table
containing the geometry of the font so
that you can draw it with proper spacing
and everything hmm
and then when you're talking about
assets that would be like textures like
for example if you had a sign in the
game that would be something that
somebody would actually have to go into
say Photoshop or something and have a
different version for each language yes
and ideally you want to keep all the
original layered versions of this with
the text on a separate layer because
that will make it as easy as possible to
change the text that's on it but of
course that isn't always available so
when it's not you need somebody who's
actually able to remove the text and put
something new in there's also things
like title screens of course and any
sort of special menu text you have like
that's drawn in a different font or has
a special design mm-hmm because I guess
you know something in Japanese versus
something in English can look
significantly different when you're
doing a logo or something so you need
someone with the sort of artistic
expertise to be able to to recreate
something that look like the other thing
right yes and of course Japanese logos
are often written entirely in Japanese
so you want to come up with a localized
title for these games and then put it in
the correct localized language and that
will involve basically designing a new
logo that looks similar it gets the same
point across which is the big thing in
localization you want to get the point
across mm-hmm one of the games you
worked on was a game where you decided
that the game's code needed to be
rewritten
can you kind of talk a little bit about
what the game is and why you decided
that you needed to rewrite the game well
in this case we are talking about a game
called corpse party corpse parties
origins were as an RPG maker came on an
obscure Japanese computer obscure over
here at least and when the developers
revisited it many years later they
decided to remake it in a programming
language called hot soup processor or
HSP for short and HSP was taught in many
Japanese schools because it was free and
it was made for people wanting to get
into things like this now a hot soup
processor resembles basically the child
of Java and C and in this way everything
is a little different I wouldn't even
compare it to C honestly more like basic
and as a result your game looks more
like a scripting language than a
programming language and the bigger
problem is that you don't have as much
control over the graphics and sound
api's for games that are coded in HSP
and so to do many things with the
graphics properly or get the timer's
right it may be better to change over to
something else especially if you're
going to put this game on something like
steam because steam does not have a
version of their API for hot soup
processor I know shocking calling all
developers there's no telling what you
can create when you upgrade your data
platform to inner system's iris are you
ready to build the applications you want
however you want them are you ready to
develop applications faster than ever
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today inner system's
iris data platform ready set code
start coding for free visit enter
systems.com slash try to try iris when
you're talking about it being like basic
is there kind of like a high reliance on
like go-to statements or just kind of
curious what the language looks like
unfortunately yes there is
was this a statically type what was it
like to kind of work in that language
well when it comes to typing you don't
always know what type it's gonna be you
don't know if this variable is
necessarily an integer or if it's a
float and the compiler of the scripts
largely doesn't care and obviously that
means you can run into some typing
issues because you have completely
misunderstood what a variable actually
was that definitely gave me some
headaches so it's sort of more like say
JavaScript or Ruby where you can define
a variable and that variable you could
put in a string you could put in a
number you could put in pretty much
anything and there isn't really a way to
check I guess it just kind of runs
through the the interpreter and then you
find out at runtime whether something's
gonna blow up pretty much pretty much I
definitely would compare it to Ruby in
that regard so what was your your
strategy for rewriting a game like were
you porting function by function kind of
how did you get started of course I
started by just copying all of the code
and then I began rewriting each function
one at a time trying my best to
understand the purpose of each function
as I was going along I knew what some of
them did already because we actually
inserted the translation before all of
this but the thing is that I was never
going to be sure exactly what functions
relied on each other and what variables
were needed and how exactly they needed
to be typed until everything was already
basically put together and so I honestly
was pretty scared during this process at
times because I had no idea it was gonna
work until it worked mmm you were
rebuilding it
by function but because it wasn't really
clear which functions relied on other
functions you couldn't actually run the
game like there wasn't like this
iteration of you got part of it working
and you can see it and you move on to
the next part you had to almost build
everything and then you found out if
there were issues yes exactly because
for the most part with games you are not
building the code level by level you are
programming something that will be able
to run all of the levels well that
sounds terrifying were you able to sort
of at least on a function by function
level have an idea of what the function
was supposed to return and so you could
at least test certain functions yes
there were definitely cases like that
however the most complex parts of the
game are often more in the graphics and
audio engines and such if you're working
at this kind of level and I wasn't
always sure how the graphics functions
worked no faults the developers just
that it was so much and so you know
since you didn't quite understand how
the graphics functions worked when you
rewrote that portion of the game did you
kind of take a different approach rather
than trying to recreate what they had
done
well I initially tried to recreate what
they've done although for certain API
functions etc I basically took my best
guess and so when the game was finally
running it definitely didn't look or
sound right at first there were problems
and these were entirely problems with
how I had understood the code rather
than anything to do with the game itself
of course how long did it take from sort
of the start of getting the code to
actually being able to run the game at
all well the original version of the
game pretty much worked out of box and
compiling it I just needed the version
of the HSP tools that the game had been
made for but when it came to actually
making my version of the game ran it
took about a year well so a year before
you could launch the game yeah Wow
that's pretty intense
believe me I hated myself for a lot of
that project I was like why didn't I
just use the original code why did I put
myself through this but the result was
that the game runs very well yeah you
know it's interesting because I think
one of the sort of I guess common pieces
of advice people get when they work on
software is quick iteration in terms of
build the things see if it works then
you can build the next thing but in this
case it seems like that just straight it
wasn't possible to do yeah unfortunately
with games everything is going to be
more tangled and depending on the way
you actually approached creating the
game you can end up with either
something that's very clean and parts
don't depend too much on each other more
abstracted or it can be a plate of
spaghetti right and just like any
application this is a matter of
designing the application before you
start building it mm-hmm
one of the things that he managed to do
when you rewrote the game was I believe
you made it sort of platform agnostic
what are some examples of ways that when
you write a game you make it something
that can be easily run on on different
platforms regardless is a platform you
are going to be dealing with different
graphics and audio api's because you
know you're not gonna run DirectX on a
ps4 and essentially the approach you
need to take this is mostly related to
creating wrapper functions for all of
the graphics stuff you need to do so
that you can easily change these
functions and not have to change any
other part of the code for example you
want to have functions for a drawing of
sprite you want to have functions for
drawing some text and you want these to
be things that you can easily change the
contents of without changing any part of
the actual game's code directly and I
guess the parts that are going to be
different from platform to platform
would you say that
like the graphics the sound the input
that that sort of thing yes basically
everything that deals with IO aside from
the fact that on pretty much any
platform you're going to be able to use
like F open without any issue mm-hmm
when you rewrote the game I think you
had said that when you got the original
version of the game you had replaced the
text was that hard-coded into the game
or was that through scripting files
mostly scripting files but it took me
quite a bit of effort to understand
these scripting files there definitely
was some hard-coded text in the game
mostly related to the menu functions
like chapter names for example that you
would encounter in the menus were
hard-coded and when you did the rewrite
did your rewrite load in the original
script file format yes actually
although interestingly enough with this
particular game all of the original
scripts were in Japanese like even the
commands and this is not common it does
happen but usually the commands and such
will be roughly in English because when
you're working with programming you're
going to be writing some of it in
English no matter what language you
speak but since all these scripts were
completely in Japanese I decided to
replace all of the commands such that on
the game could still load for the
original format but it was using
something sort of new in that the script
commands were simply translated and when
you refer to like a script command could
you give an example of what some of
those would be well stuff like message
weight display picture move character to
the left or you know stuff like that
or check a variable it's a lot like
programming it's just that you are
working in a language that is created
for the game and is being used by the
game without compilation usually
sometimes there's assembly involved but
when you assemble a script like this you
are just converting the commands to 1 2
3 etc and to make sure that you know
what the commands are without having to
use as much text in space
okay so it's kind of like like an enum
it's that a good example yeah
essentially and those commands they
would use the English letters but they
would just be written in Japanese words
they were actually written in shift-jis
full Japanese Wow okay I never
encountered any other project did that
although I understand it must have made
the script files really easy to
understand for them yeah it's kind of
interesting how you know we sort of make
the assumption when we look at code that
there's going to be English in it but
yeah I guess sometimes you get surprised
yeah for the most part there aren't many
programming languages where you can do
everything in another language but if
you're creating the language yourself
obviously you have plenty of control
over that and you can do anything and so
even though we sort of take for granted
that there's going to be English there
doesn't have to be and I find that
extremely interesting I don't know that
it happens it's very often but I think a
lot of languages do support Unicode for
variable names and stuff like that I
just am not sure how many people
actually take advantage of that yeah
when it comes to seeing localized
variable names and source' that are not
in the normal character set I would say
I hardly ever see it mm-hmm I can only
think of one occasion and like people
usually instead find that it is written
in English characters but is in that
language which in the case of Japanese
is what they call romaji
so you would have the Japanese written
entirely in letters and you find that a
lot when you're localizing Japanese
games mmm you know you said kind of
after the year you were able to run the
game but there were bugs or there were
different issues how are you able to
sort of track down what bugs were in the
game I mean was it a completely manual
process where you just had to keep
playing and keep trying things
essentially as well as having testers
within the company also handles that
handle that sort of testing what is
called of course Quality Assurance of
course we just call it QA but by having
people iterate
through the game many times we would
find all of the dogs with it essentially
like he would any other program you just
have to have people using it with their
any kind of bugs or odd behavior in the
original version that the game was
relying on that you had to reproduce I
wouldn't say there were any bugs that he
had to reproduce but since I had copied
the games code as closely as possible
some of the original bugs did carryover
initially and I was later able to fix a
lot of them cool and you know we've kind
of been talking about the process of
making games and sort of rewriting games
like what is the language that you
rewrote the game in C++ is that pretty
typical for the projects you you work on
that the games are written in C++ I
would say that the vast majority of
professional games are written in C++
what would you say makes that sort of
the default choice or the the main
choice that people would go to frankly
it is widely supported you have C++
compilers for consoles you have them for
computers you have them for all kinds of
different devices whereas you create a
game in Ruby you have no idea if you're
going to be able to put that on a
Playstation 4 mm-hmm so it's kind of
just the fact that everybody is using it
and there's so many tools so much
support yeah exactly as well as the
fairly robust standard libraries and
since these are available in so many
platforms it's just always been the
choice ever since it came to be
originally back in the days of like the
Nintendo Entertainment System games were
primarily written in rolla sembly but
obviously that's not very practical
especially for the scale of games these
days so it eventually changed to see and
then C++ there have been efforts to
adopt C sharpen more platforms but it's
kind of slow going because it's just so
deep-rooted yeah I think like typically
when I hear about c-sharp and games it's
within the context of say
the unity engine and it seems like that
would make it easier for people to sort
of get started and and work on projects
but I don't know what the trade-offs are
you know relative to C++ typically I
would say that C++ simply is the most
easy to optimize compared to other
options like this because of the nature
of how it's compiled whereas with
c-sharp they take a more native approach
where all of the code is you know it's
native code and managed code and the
native code is easier to optimize
whereas the managed code that makes up
most of c-sharp simply isn't something
you can optimize much beyond how it's
handled for everything it's a global
optimization whereas optimization
specific to various functions and games
are better than global optimization in a
case like this the trade-off is simply
performance how much you can pull out of
the system before it starts choking
mm-hmm and one of the big differences
between the two languages is that
c-sharp has a garbage collector for
games is that something that's typically
seen as as not desirable
rather than having garbage collection
you need to handle all of the games
memory very very strictly you need to
know exactly how much memory everything
is going to take at any given time the
reason for this is because consoles
typically have much more severe memory
limitations than a computer does and if
you start running over that memory you
just don't have a program running
anymore it's problematic
whereas on PC there are of course things
like virtual memory to pick up if you
end up running out of memory somehow and
as a result if you have any sort of
garbage collection you're going to be
wanting to do it yourself
frankly all memory that you're
allocating you should be doing yourself
you should have your own memory back
sure in the game hmm I see and then you
said like it's probably true for all
platforms but on consoles it's more
important just because of the memory
restrictions yes and of course that is
so why when you are porting the game to
a console you have to be very
considerate of things like memory space
and of course video RAM if it's more
important back in the older days systems
like the Super Nintendo the Nintendo 64
but it still remains important today if
you start running out of memory on a
console there's nothing you can do about
it mm-hmm
you've ported some games from low spec
hardware like the PlayStation Portable
to the PC what are some of the unique
challenges related to porting a game
well first of all when it comes to a
game on an older system or weaker
systems such as the PlayStation Portable
the game is made exactly for the
hardware specifications and you are at
the mercy of those specifications at
first
for example the PlayStation Portable its
resolution is quite small it is
something like 480 by 272 and while that
is almost 16:9 it's not quite when it
comes to PC games people want options
they want the ability to use different
resolutions and customize their controls
and the original game is probably not
going to have supported this and more
importantly if you're working at a game
at a low resolution like that that is
not going to look good on a PC screen so
we actually with these projects we take
as many of the original PSD assets and
such as we can and just redo the games
assets in HD and that obviously results
in a much prettier game but that also
assumes that you actually made the
assets and higher resolution to begin
with otherwise they're going to have to
be remade and that is a whole different
ballpark of problems
yeah the resolution is so low that if
you were to use the original assets they
would just look super super blurry or
blocky if you were to to port it
straight to the PC exactly right and
frankly that would make the game look
a lot worse a whole and less people
would play it because at that point
you're just playing something that looks
old and you don't want it to look old
because you're creating a new version of
it you want it to look new and shiny and
sparkly how would you say the process of
porting a game differs from your
experience say you know rewriting the
game with corpse party you know how much
of it is a rewrite versus something
different well when you're porting the
game hopefully it's in a language that
you can still use and if that's the case
then the first step is more going to be
ripping out all the stuff that you can't
use for example when you're working on a
console you have to use the console
developers development kit and
everything you have to use their
software and well usually the supports
the same programming languages that you
would be able to use on PC anyway you
won't be able to use most of the
graphics functions and the audio
functions and you're just going to have
to do all of that over instead of
copying like I did when I was porting
one language to another I instead had to
basically take guesses at what all of
these functions did and then reproduce
them to my best and occasionally this
would result in something I didn't
understand just like when I was working
on the original corpse party game but
more often I would find that I missed a
functionality and that something
wouldn't change color when it was
supposed to or something wouldn't play
from the correct speaker or things like
that and one of the latest issues that I
got when I was working on my first parts
like last minute was that I realized
there were audio files that were
supposed to be looping and crossfading
and I had forgotten to implement any of
this because I didn't realize what it
was and so when it comes to porting to
PC there are two main concerns one is
making sure all the functionality is
correct in the first place and the
second is making sure that the game runs
well on a PC because
there are different threading models and
different sorts of timer models that
simply don't convert well to a PC and
that's the case with changing platforms
in general you want to make sure that
everything runs as it should even though
it's on a different platform which I
know I'm just speaking in circles there
but at the same time you have to realize
if you just put a game directly on PC
and you don't change anything it is
going to run a lot slower than it could
because it was optimized for something
else and when you talk about the
different threading models could you
give an example of you know something
running on a console versus on a PC what
are these different threading models or
different choices you would be looking
at well for example let's say that you
are programming a game that is working
on a Nintendo Wii you will find that you
have to handle the graphics at this time
and the audio at this time and threading
is often a better choice when it's
available for simple performance reasons
however it's also the case that a lot of
older games don't use any sort of
threads at all everything is just a
single thread going through that single
game loop and you have to deal with the
results as they come but when it comes
to a PC game you of course want threads
you want to be able to use more of the
CPUs and instead of using the exact CPU
number and types that you have on the
console like that you have this audio
and this CPU and this console happens to
have a dedicated audio processor stuff
like that you want to use something more
general on a PC that'll work on anything
yeah so in terms of I guess concurrency
models on a console the software
development kit for that console may
already have sort of ways that you're
required to do certain things like you
were saying a certain way to do graphics
a certain way to do audio and once you
bring it to PC
then you have more control over how you
do concurrency how you do graphics and
so you may choose to do it completely
differently than how it originally
worked yes and I think in many cases
that's preferable because obviously
concurrency and something like a game is
best used for optimization and making
sure that everything runs smoothly
without any hitches but on a console you
are optimizing to such a specific
scenario that this optimization does not
carry over well and is actually harmful
when you are copying it directly to a PC
are there any specific API is for
example OpenGL you know that you would
choose when you want to make something
that you can consistently use across
platforms I would choose OpenGL or
possibly STL because surprisingly STL
exists for quite a lot of platforms that
said I would say that Vulcan is becoming
something that would be very useful in
that sort of way in terms of the
projects that you've worked on the
example you gave with PlayStation
Portable were those games using some
kind of API specific to the console to
you know to do graphics rendering to do
audio all that sort of thing yes the API
is for these things are typically
provided by the unn development kit and
whether they resemble an existing API or
not is pretty much up to the console
creators choice for example if you're
working on a Nintendo 3ds you can
probably use OpenGL straight up with
just a few changes
although the optimization is still going
to be a nightmare by comparison because
it is completely different when you're
working on one of these ports have you
ever kind of had to go the other way
around where you had a less constrained
environment and then had to move it to a
more constrained environment so far I
would say no because for the most part
PC is about the least constrained you'll
get but I still try to make sure that
when I'm working on a game it will run
on as many systems as possible and that
means trying to make it run on
toaster if I could and when your PC is a
potato you don't really expect a fully
3d game to work right but sometimes they
can sometimes if you are very careful
about the way you optimize the game and
do take a lot of constraints in what
you're doing you will make a game that
looks a lot better than it should on an
older PC and I try to make that a goal
of mine I try to make sure that these
games run in older environments up until
last year I was even making a point of
supporting Windows XP with all of my
games and that would be more of an issue
at times than you would think mmm what's
an example of something that you would
have to do specifically for such an old
operating system for supporting old
operating systems you essentially are
limited when it comes to your compilers
and your libraries you can't use newer
versions of libraries because they
weren't made for older systems the
Windows kernel changed very dramatically
with Windows Vista and it's only been
evolving more and more sense and you are
limited to using this older version of
the kernel that is largely still
supported but there's often behaviors
that are just a little different between
a system and you won't expect them like
you might be trying to get the size of
your window rectangle and it will be off
by one small things like that or you'll
be drawing text and Vista might support
outlining the text and XP might not so
there's like subtle bugs or small
features that just don't exist so when
you have to take into account you know
whether you'll have those or not it just
makes everything more complicated yes
exactly and you don't always have the
ability to expect it because often the
functions will look the same but the
behavior is simply different mm-hm and
these are operating system level calls
that you're referring to yes largely
although there's also the matter of
api's for things like graphics that
don't exist on all their operating
systems for example you can't use
directx 10 or later on XP one of the
things about porting is we were talking
about the things that you you can't
really reuse is the the core game loop
and the logic as most of that are you
able to use as is without modification
well for the most part most of the game
code is going to stay intact like that
you will have to alter stuff like the
coordinate calls for various textures
because all of a sudden you're worried
about different resolutions games
running on consoles they generally run
on a single resolution that is their
target and if you are using a different
resolution on your TV the console is
scaling the output to that but when you
are working on PC you need to account
for that and you need to account for
different aspect ratios because while
it's easy to say oh I'm gonna make my
game this resolution you might upset the
people who have ultra wide monitors or
the people who are still using old 4:3
monitors they exist and ideally you want
to support all of these scenarios as
smoothly as you can when you're creating
a game you can account for this better
than if you're working on a game that
already exists yeah so it sounds like
that's a lot of work in general in terms
of finding the sections of code that are
expecting a specific resolution a
specific aspect ratio and like earlier
you were talking about how your assets
may change as well because you know you
need UI elements that can be rendered at
a much higher resolution or at a
different sort of shape so it seems like
there's a lot of work that needs to go
into it yes a lot of the games that I
worked on earlier in my career were
older games that were made for 4:3 and
in the process of working on these I
realized obviously these games need to
be widescreen and so there were a lot of
different approaches that could be taken
I could have converted the entire games
to widescreen but then what about the
purists so I made this approach where I
could arbitrarily in the code set any
graphic to be aligned to the left or
right of the screen
or at the center essentially by dividing
the screen into regions that were still
4:3 so for example I would draw a UI
element that was always in the bottom
right of the screen on the right and
when the aspect ratio increases this
would still be drawn on the right of the
screen in the corner and by separating
out HUD elements like this it gives a
fairly consistent experience between
different platforms without having to
limit the user to a specific aspect
ratio mm-hmm you've worked on a lot of
different games that have been made at a
long time ago or more recently what are
some of the big differences code wise I
guess you've seen in like the oldest
projects you've worked on versus the
newer ones well I actually got my start
in fan translation working on things in
assembly you know disassembly rather and
obviously the challenges for that are
very apparent you're working with very
raw code that you don't have any
information on but as I've gone along I
worked on various Japanese indie games
as well as Japanese professional titles
and as the time has gone along I feel
that on average these games are more
abstracted and more object oriented and
back then there was very little object
orientation there were just these loops
and loops upon loops nowadays you'll
have various objects that might be
inherited from other objects so a
videogames character might be a single
generic object that has most of the
basic behaviors and then on top of that
you will have the class for the player
character or the class for a dragon and
they have their own unique stuff to them
and obviously the game loop has changed
a lot over the years as a result of
things like this yeah it's it's
interesting because I think that I guess
matches how software development in
general has maybe evolved because there
used to be you know primarily just
procedural code right
and now we're seeing more
object-oriented code more code related
to functional programming and so so
maybe that parallels the the general
software community yes I believe so in
this regard the evolution does seem
pretty parallel the only limiting factor
is that adoption of new programming
languages is very slow mm-hmm
yeah I'm not even sure what they would
have used before C++ C oh right but
before that they really did just program
games in basic assembly and occasionally
in basic yeah yeah and you were
mentioning how you know you had actually
worked on fan translations where you
would have to reverse engineer the code
and you said that was with assembly yes
because when it comes to these games
that are already compiled and you're
working on them as a fan you're not
gonna have any access to the source code
ever so there are two options available
to you from there you can either learn
how to work with the code that's already
compiled by learning the assembly and
learning how to debug this or you can in
some cases to an extent D compile the
code if it was made in an existing
framework that's well understood like
dotnet or some other programming
languages that exist but usually you're
gonna be working with the raw assembly
when you're working as a fan and you
need a strong understanding of the
processor that the game was developed
for and the exact sort of quirks to
expect yeah so when you're working you
know as a fan you actually somehow have
to determine I guess where the text is
in that game right even though
everything is just raw assembly so what
is kind of the approach for doing that
how would you even know where to start
well initially you would have a debugger
that works with the game and you would
have to step through step by step until
you actually see the text being drawn
and then you basically start stepping
back from there to see how the text was
loaded and so it's all a process of
finding
first something that use the function
you need to edit and then working your
way back yeah that sounds very very
time-consuming I guess but it's an
interesting process because you've
learned a lot about how different styles
are used in different things
hmm because then not only would you have
to to find the text but you would have
to find a way to reinsert it without you
know the application breaking yeah and
in some cases the text would be stored
in the application itself but usually
it's gonna be in some sort of container
you don't have any specifications for
and then it might be in some encoding
you don't know it might even be
encrypted and obviously all of the
functions for you to fix that are right
there but how do you put it back in
because it's easier to extract something
than it is to create an archive that
works exactly as the one before yeah
that's interesting because you're yeah
like you said you have these files where
you don't know kind of how they're
encoded but you're looking through the
assembly code to maybe get a hint for
how they were generated so you can
modify or generate them yourself exactly
and when it comes to compressions and
encryptions it definitely is much easier
to get a file that's already encrypted
or encoded or compressed open than it is
to make a new one because you have to
worry about the size of the file you
have to worry about getting the
optimization of the compression right
you mess up one part of the encryption
key and everything was wrong
that sounds like pretty intense work for
a fan project yeah I actually got my
start working on just simple script
engines in games like 4k dia of all
things when I was young but as it went
along I discovered things like emulation
and all these interesting games in a
language I didn't understand and all I
could think was how could these games be
English is there a way and sure enough
there actually was yeah that's that's
really really impressive and
very cool you know that kind of brings
me to for somebody who's interested in
you know modifying or localizing games
how would you recommend someone today
sort of get started well I would find a
project that you like on something like
github and simply try changing things
and improving things in that first make
it your own
essentially with something like this you
need to get comfortable working in other
people's code it's not about learning to
program a program yourself it's about
learning to be comfortable in other
shoes and being able to cope with the
decisions they make yeah that's a really
interesting perspective because I feel
like general software development a lot
of it is is also that right because so
many of the projects people work on
they're they're not brand new there's
something that you know a team has been
working on for years and you're kind of
coming into that environment living with
the decisions that were made and
figuring out where to go from there yes
with normal game development you'll find
all sorts of tutorials that teach you
how to build a basic platforming game
engine or such but it won't necessarily
tell you why it's built that way and you
can make games that way but you can't
really work with somebody else's games
from tutorials like that it has to all
be about putting in the footwork
yourself and just trying you just have
to try and you just have to keep doing
it until it gets right just like any
other skill for sure you know after all
the years of experience you've had
aren't there certain things that you do
really differently now than what you did
before oh definitely for one I used to
do absolutely everything by hand when it
comes to even stuff like text I used to
copy the text and paste it into files as
I needed it and rinse and repeat and
when I was working this fan translator
sometimes early on I would change the
pointers for the text manually when I
needed more space and that is just an
awful idea automate as much as you can
make sure that whatever you're doing
you're doing it the easiest way you can
but at the same time don't sacrifice
quality for this but typically you won't
mm-hmm so basically like find the things
I guess that you are doing that are sort
of repetitive try and identify the
things that you can automate and build
that script or build whatever
functionality you need yes exactly
because if you're spending a lot of time
pulling the text out or something like
that you obviously don't need to be
there are cases where you might want to
do that like if there's exactly one or
two hard-coded strings or just a single
menu but if the project are working is
that any sort of scale that makes that
an hours-long job to not do it manually
please for sure yeah I think that
applies broadly as well it's kind of
like how much pain do you need to feel
before it's like just you know just get
it done just just automate it write that
write that script that's exactly the
beauty of being a programmer is you
shouldn't need to do much math because
you can make the program do it for you
well so I think it's a good place to
kind of start wrapping up but is there
anything else that you thought we should
have mentioned or talked about hmm I
suppose another thing I would like to
mention is if you're getting into
localization programming for a specific
language like Japanese to English or
something like that you should probably
try to learn as much of the language as
you can along the way so not just the
programming language but the actual
language as well if you are working on
Japanese games a lot knowing Japanese
makes your work so much easier what are
some of the the ways that you found that
knowing the language really helped you a
lot well put simply even though all of
the text for a programming language is
just gonna be you know and like ASCII
you're going to be dealing with the fact
that all of the comments are going to be
in another language a lot of the
function names are going to be in
another language you're going to see a
file
named Zack oh and you're not gonna know
that that means a small fry enemy yes
they're just helping you get as many I
guess hints and context as you can yeah
exactly because when you're working on
someone else's code in another language
you are not going to be working with
documentation you can necessarily read
all of the documentation is absolutely
going to be in that language yeah yeah
for sure I guess code comments as well
if those exist I do usually cool for
people who are kind of interested in
checking out what you're working on or
what you're up to
how can they they follow you first of
all obviously you should keep up with
exceeds work in general if you want to
keep up with what I'm doing
but I also have twitter saara jaylene sa
ra j J oh yeah and I also occasionally
do twitch streams not of programming but
as games in general and my twitch
username is sa RA L II and II sort of a
corruption of my name you work in a very
unique field of software development and
I really enjoyed the conversation
saara thank you so much for sharing your
experience translating and porting games
thank you for giving me a chance to talk
about the technical side of things yeah
it was really fun so thanks again for
coming on the show my pleasure this is
Jeremy Jung for a software engineering
video thanks for listening developers
take your marks it's time to upgrade
your data platform to inner systems iris
it's time to deliver complex
mission-critical applications in the
fastest route possible it's time to use
any data from any source it's time to
embed analytics and create interactive
user interfaces so what are you waiting
for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
inner system's iris Data Platform the
fastest way to build applications ready
set code start coding for free visit
inner systems.com slash tried to try
iris
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening